<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise concerning estates tayle and discents of inheritance written by N.N. ; and published by I. Sherman ...</title>
            <author>N. N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N61</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12334631</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12334631</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59742</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52908)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59742)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1019:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise concerning estates tayle and discents of inheritance written by N.N. ; and published by I. Sherman ...</title>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
                  <author>Sherman, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42, [i.e. 43] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Grove ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 42, 43 misnumbered 43 and 42, respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inheritance and succession --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59742:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59742:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE Concerning Eſtates Tayle, and Diſcents of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>N. N.</hi> and Publiſhed by <hi>I. SHERMAN,</hi> of Lincolnes Inne: <hi>Gen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Grove,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Chancery Lane,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Subpaena</hi> Office. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:59742:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59742:2"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe concerning Eſtates Tayle, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcents of Inheritance.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou demand (good Sir) if Eſtates tayle may bee cut off? whereto I may ſhortly anſwer, that every Act for the lawfull execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of requires power and will, without both which onely things caſuall are accompliſhed; the will naming the worke good or bad, the power giving ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to finiſh what the will freely inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59742:3"/>
This power may truely bee called poſſibility, inabled either by Nature, or by Law; for that which is unnaturall or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our natures, is not judged poſſible or in our powers; no more is that which is to be done againſt the Lawes: for we have no due power to doe ought that is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, all our powers being ſubject unto Law; for <hi>illud poſſumus quod jure poſſumus:</hi> Now touching the power and authority, to avoyd eſtates taile, it is plaine that as the making of them was authorized by the Stat. of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. ſo by the Stat. of 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 24, and 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 36. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in taile may lawfully cut them off: ſince therefore the power to create an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate taile, and the power to barre the Iſſue in taile are equally warranted by Law; for <hi>apari poteſtate par cauſatur effectus,</hi> the next doubt will be if our wills or affections to cut them off doe ſort to a lawfull end; which end though it be laſt in execution, yet ought it to be firſt Cenſured; as the firſt part of all our actions: and touching
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59742:3"/>
this point, I muſt referre my ſelfe to every man his peculiar conſcience, who can beſt make anſwer in this behalfe what hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth: onely I muſt note by the way, that ſuch as avoyd and cut off theſe eſtates to none other purpoſe but to enlarge their wanton expences, and to give them more ſcope to live licentiouſly, as they unjuſtly ſpoile their Heires of their due Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo ſhall not this my defence extend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; ſince my purpoſe onely is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce eſtates taile to the moſt proper conveyance of the Common Law. And becauſe ſometime the effects produced of our actions are taken for their ends, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are to be valued; And ſince the fruſtrating of eſtates taile diſpoſeth it ſelfe to none other end then to ſet at liberty theſe fettered Inheritances: To prove therefore whether Inheritance at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, or theſe Statutes, or conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall gifts are to be preferred; it behoveth me to ſhew you what an Inheritance is, and what an eſtate taile is, that ſo you may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59742:4"/>
more eaſily conceive their differences. In the Civill Law Inheritance is <hi>Succeſſio in univerſum jus quod defunctus habebat,</hi> which definition doth well agree with our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, which ſaith, that an Inheritance is ſuch an eſtate as may be inherited by the Heire, which eſtate doth naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the Heire; as if it were joyned and included in him by a violent motion of the Law: and this diſcent is that which the Civilians call ſucceſſion, and our Common Lawyers Inheritance: which ſo cleaveth to the Heire, as if the Father diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiſeth a ſtranger, and dyeth ſeiſed; this Land ſhall diſcend to the Heire againſt his will, and he is Tenant to the precipe though hee never enters. And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall Lands purchaſed diſcend, except the Purchaſor doth ſome Act to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and except in caſes of Attainder: by this I gather that Inheritance is the Act of the Law; for <hi>Nemo eſt haeres viventis,</hi> no man is Heire of him that is living, and dead men have no power to chuſe their Heires:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59742:4"/>
therefore I ſay it muſt follow that this diſcent is the act of the Law, and diſ-inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting, or altering the courſe of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, the act of the party. The conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion now muſt be, if the Act of the perſon may juſtly make voyd the Act of the Law; wherein we muſt conſider the force of the Lawes, and the hability of perſons: firſt therefore Law as St. <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith, is <hi>Quaedam rationis ordinatio ad bonum commune,</hi> a certaine diſpoſition of reaſon to common good; which diſpoſition is (by <hi>Frigius</hi>) called a <hi>Coercion</hi> of things voluntary, and not vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary; whereby it ſeemeth that if wee will be reaſonable creatures, we muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelves to the governance of the Law, which as it is ſaid, is the diſpoſition of reaſon, and the <hi>Coercion</hi> of our wills offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding reaſon: the Law therefore as a mute Magiſtrate compelleth us to her obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, warranteth us ſafety under her Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get; and though Lawes were made for men, yet were they not made to rule men, by which I gather, that Lawes are ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59742:5"/>
to men, and men inferiour to Lawes; the Acts therefore of the Lawes are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amount, or above the Acts of the party; and to draw this my preſent purpoſe, ſince the diſcent of Inheritance in Fee-ſimple is wrought onely by the Law; and ſince theſe gifts entaile are the naturall iſſues of mens fantaſies, why might I not here conclude that our eſtimation of eſtates taile ought to be much inferiour to that eſtate which the Common Law createth? howbeit ſince this hath bin ſpoken generally, and confuſedly of all Lawes, and ſince wee are in this government ſubject to divers ſorts of Lawes in divers reſpects, it behooveth me to ſhew you what Lawes doe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concerne this matter, and how Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritances are reſpected in either of them; and ſince Fee-ſimples, and eſtates taile are oppoſite in their natures, and ſince like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Adage ſaith, <hi>Ferro aperire viam qui per contraria tranſit,</hi> I will prove unto you that the proper and naturall diſcent of Fee-ſimple is good, and lawfull in all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59742:5"/>
Lawes, by which meanes it will follow, that eſtates taile being contrary to Fee-ſimple are not good, nor lawfull, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries agree not: Lawes therefore are either Divine or humane, and divine Lawes are either Lawes of nature, or Lawes delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But before I ſpeake of humane Lawes, I ſhall firſt ſhew you that the forme of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which the Common Law ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, agreeth with the Lawes of nature; and ſo by conſequence with the Lawes of God: for proofe whereof it were enough, conſidering the perſpicuity of the Matter, if I ſhould uſe the authority of <hi>Plowden,</hi> who ſaith that nothing in our Common Law is ordained againſt nature, and yet our Common Law will that Inheritances ſhall deſcend to the Heire: but to prove it more particularly, the firſt Act that nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires is to procreate, the ſecond to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, the third to provide for ſuſtenance, which proviſion comprehendeth the whole effect of Inheritances: and in the Civill law it is called <hi>haereditas legitima,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59742:6"/>
which is ſaid to appertaine moſt properly to the Father his office, as <hi>haereditas naturalis</hi> which conſiſts in nouriſhing and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, belongs to the Mother, and though natures lawes which are onely written in our hearts, have not expreſſed in any lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner that this proviſion or Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, belongeth more to the Heire then to the reſt of our Children, or Kindred, yet hath the continuall practiſe of all ages teſtified unto us, that the lawes of nature would wee ſhould leave our Inheritances, firſt rather <hi>natis</hi> then <hi>agnatis,</hi> rather to our Children then to our Couſins, and rather to Sonnes then to Daughters; and if wee have Sonnes, we have likewiſe a Rule that ſaith, <hi>Proximus excludit remotiorem,</hi> and in all governments the eldeſt Sonnes are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted either to all, or moſt part of the Inheritance, and in want of Sonnes, Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for whom nature injoynes us rather to provide then for more remote Couſins: and theſe generall received Cuſtomes of all; times and places are the beſt meanes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59742:6"/>
we have to interpret the lawes of nature, which are onely delivered to us in exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of times paſt. The ſecond part of God his Lawes are the lawes written, wherein the omnipotent Maker of the world hath diſcovered unto us in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Words, what his high pleaſure is we ſhould doe concerning Inheritances: and though I be not ſo skilfull in theſe lawes as I ought to be, yet I have noted out of the Prophet, that he would not ſo much as ſuffer the firſt begotten ſonne, even of the hated Wife to bee diſ-inherited; neither ought any man to take example of ſome Holy men, who have croſſed this courſe of Inheritance, conſidering that it hath alwayes hapned either by the expreſſe Commandement of Almighty God, and ſo was <hi>Adonai</hi> diſ-inherited by King <hi>David</hi> his father, and the Inheritance beſtowed on <hi>Salomon</hi> a younger brother; or elſe it chanced for ſome notable crime by the Heire, and ſo was <hi>Reuben</hi> the Heire of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> diſ-inherited, and his Inheritance given
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59742:7"/>
to the Sonnes of <hi>Joſeph:</hi> and this I have repeated to none other purpoſe then to prove, firſt that Inheritances are agreeable to the lawes of nature; and laſtly that they are commanded by the expreſſe lawes of God, and therefore ought not but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſpeciall cauſe bee violated: ſince I have ſhewed you what I have gathered out of Divine lawes concerning Inheritances, it followeth that I ſpeake ſomewhat of humane lawes, and namely of our common lawes, for by them are Inheritances onely managed in this government; except in ſome peculiar places, where Cuſtome, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the daughter of errour, hath indenized and made free degenerating formes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances, as of Gavel kinde, and Burgh <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which cuſtome I muſt here omit, as more fit for another place; to ſhew you what our common law is, and what kind of Inheritance it produceth, that ſo by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring what entailes are not, I may diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what they are: our Common law im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth his definition in his name, for it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59742:7"/>
called <hi>Commune jus, quaſi Communis juſtitia;</hi> common Juſtice, and it is divided into two parts, old and new; the ancient are ſuch as whereof wee neither know begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nor ending, and in theſe lawes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes were utterly unknowne, and our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances were diſpoſed in the act of the law, onely by diſcent in Fee-ſimple, which as Mr. <hi>Littleton</hi> ſaith, is <hi>haereditas legitima vel pura,</hi> and this Fee-ſimple was ſetled on the Heire and his heires by a perpetuall opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the law. Another ſort of Fee-ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples conditionall there was likewiſe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, but this condition was no adition of the law, but onely a reſtraint of the donor, which reſtraint was uſed by our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers inſtead of eſtates taile, tying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Inheritance to the iſſue of the body of the Donee, but ſaving to the donor no Reverſion, or at moſt but a Title, or poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of a Reverſion for want of Heires of the body of the Donee, for Fee-ſimple ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth no Reverſion, yet could not the Donee alien his eſtate before he had iſſue,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59742:8"/>
and by having iſſue ſetled the Inheritance in him; then was this Title, or right to this Reverſion of no longer eſtimation in our law: and this appeareth by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute that ſaith <hi>poſt prolem habuit poteſtatem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enandi,</hi> which liberty of the alienation (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had iſſue) in mine opinion was juſt and reaſonable; and herein ſhall my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be eaſily ratified, if it ſhall bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what miſchiefes might otherwiſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the tenent conditionall, if he ſhould ſtill be detained from power to alien after he had iſſue, for ſo might he be compelled to admit one, peradventure none of his, or an unworthy heire of vile condition, which no extremity of law requireth: our Common-law therefore nothing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting the fathers care to preſerve his Inheritance for his heire, gave to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after hee had iſſue power to alien at his pleaſure, that ſo he might retaine this power as a bridle to reſtraine the unruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Youth, who in his education would peradventure doe better for hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59742:8"/>
then for feare of puniſhment; or at leaſt doe beſt being compelled by them both, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd hereof I would onely gather that Common law is common Juſtice; and that the ordinary ſort of Inheritances com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Law of God, &amp; that though Fee-ſimple conditionall ſomewhat ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth from the purity of Fee-ſimple, yet that the reſtraint of the Donee his aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the benefit of the donor was juſt untill the Donee had iſſue; and that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Donee his liberty to alien after (by having iſſue) he had ſetled the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in himſelfe was likewiſe moſt juſt, and herein onely did Fee-ſimple conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally differ from gifts in taile, which by the Stat. of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. reſtrained the Donee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Deed, or feoffment from prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his iſſue.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> Section of Stat. Lawes.</head>
               <p>ANd now I ſhall for a while ceaſe to ſpeake of our ancient Lawes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ſomwhat of our newer ſorts of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59742:9"/>
lawes commonly called Statutes, which I have termed the newer ſort, becauſe wee are aſſured of the times of their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and of theſe new lawes the whole vertue conſiſts, either in commanding things neceſſary, forbidding things hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, puniſhing things unjuſt, or permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or making lawfull things otherwiſe unlawfull; concerning any of which when we call in doubt our neceſſity of obedience to them, wee muſt conſider that ſuch as juſtly command, or juſtly forbid, are of more reſpect then thoſe which onely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, ſince the price of the offence againſt Statutes puniſhing conſiſts in the meaſure of the puniſhments; but ſuch Statutes as onely permits or gives liberty to doe things unlawfull, becauſe they are but authorities to breake the lawes; therefore they are unworthily termed lawes, and by conſequence not ſo to be reſpected: with this doth St. <hi>Thomas</hi> well agree, ſaying, <hi>permiſſio non eſt officium legis quia lex adfert ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem,</hi> ſufferance or permiſſion is not the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59742:9"/>
office of the law, becauſe the law impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a necesſity, whereby I conceive that ſuch ſtatutes as neither command, forbid, nor puniſh, are left in our diſcretions to be kept or broken, except the keeping of them impugne the lawes Divine: it ſhould ſeeme therefore that ſince the making of eſtates taile was but a permiſſion, and no commandement, (for no man is compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to make them) that it remaineth as a thing indifferent to bee done or undone for ought that appeareth in our Common Lawes; and touching the cutting them off when they are made, I muſt ſay as I have ſaid before, that as they were authoriſed by Statute, ſo hath later Statutes authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the cutting them off, the making there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of them (as now it ſtands) is but an act voideable, and therefore being made ſcarcely by good advice they merit onely a voyd reputation: yea and when they were in their beſt force before 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7. or 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. though the tenent in taile was ſo girt to his eſtate as a Fine levyed by him was not able to barre his iſſue, yet our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59742:10"/>
common law ſcarcely brooking this unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall brood, carved out of mens imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, made divers incurſions and breaches upon this knotty kind of Inheritance; ſometime by diſ-continuance, ſometime by warranty lineall with aſſets, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by collaterall warranties, yea and when the ſtatute of 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7. was after made and ſcarcely thought ſufficient: in 19. <hi>H.</hi> 8. to barre the iſſue in taile by fine, the Sages of the Law perceiving that while they defended a Reverſion in the Donor which in common preſumption ſhould never happen, they ſuffered ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefes to creepe into the body of the law, and ſo many diſcommodities to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in taile, as they were inforced in the 32. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. to put that ambiguity out of doores, and by Fine to give tenent in taile abſolute power to barre his iſſue; and this I have onely ſhewed you to none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end then to acquaint you with the inception and progreſſe of theſe entailes, out of which I would note that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued not long in any firme ſort, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59742:10"/>
that a ſhort experience had manifeſted ſo many incumbrances proceeding from them: as our fore-fathers ſought all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient meanes to avoyd them; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would adventure after ſo many ſharpe experiences to intaile his land, becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes are neither warranted by God his Law, nor by the ancient common lawes of this Realme. Againe, ſince intailes are onely ſuffered to be made in ſuch manner as we cannot aſſure our ſelves that this permiſſion will prove a generall pardon for the offence committed, or a remedy for the miſchiefe that happily will enſue; and conſidering that by intayling we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbe the common forme of the moſt rightfull and approved kinds of Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, commanded by Almighty God, who cannot <hi>retractare ſuum decretum,</hi> and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our common law under which wee live, and muſt of necesſity therefore bee good. I may well gather that theſe new faſhioned gifts (being contrary and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to all purpoſes) are undoubtedly to be ſuſpected vitious or very dangerous;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59742:11"/>
what conſcience therefore ſhould any man make in undoing that which is all begun, or in avoyding that which is made voyda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of purpoſe to bee avoyded as unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table? And yet I grant that ſome tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lawes are in conſcience to bee kept according to the rule in Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> who ſaith, <hi>lex que ad bonum commune referatur &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem non excedat ejus qui ipſam condit et ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum formam juſtitiae diſtributive ſervata rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one proportionis imponat ſubditis onera &amp; deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que utilis ſit habeatque reliquas conditiones,</hi> ſuch lawes in conſcience ought to be kept, but if we examine this our law of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. wee ſhall find it as I have ſaid, no law, but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misſion to breake the law; wee ſhall find that long and often proofe hath taught us that it agreeth not with publick good, we ſhall find likewiſe that ſince wee are aſſured that this diſcent in Fee ſimple beſt pleaſeth our Lord, we have ſome cauſe to doubt whether it lyeth in man his power without ſpeciall cauſe to permit by a new law the violation of ſo holy a law, and to be ſhort, it faileth in all points that might
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59742:11"/>
preſſe our conſciences: but on the other ſide for the preſervation of Inheritances we ſhall find good matter to touch our conſciences, for <hi>quod naturalis lex et divina atque adeo etiam aeterna dictat eſſe faciendum, hoc neceſſario eſt in conſcientia faciendum.</hi> Since therefore as I have ſhewed you, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures law, and the example of all Divine lawes doe warrant our common law, in the courſe of Inheritances, we ought feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to attempt the altering of them, and without feare reduce them to proper and naturall courſe: But before I write any more of the avoyding of eſtates taile, ſince the manner of doing by recovery is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to ſome perſons, I thinke it not amiſſe to ſhew you mine opinion thereof: firſt therefore I confeſſe that Recoveries are likewiſe inſtruments uſed to cut off e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates-taile remainders and reverſions, and the cauſe why the tenent in taile is barred, is in reſpect of the aſſets onely which is or may be recovered in value; and though you may ſay that this recovery is but a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the law, yet <hi>lex fingit ubi ſubſiſtit equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> and though this value to be recovered
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59742:12"/>
is poſted over to the common Cryer, who in ordinary preſumption ſhall never bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to anſwer all values recovered againſt him; yet if the father whom the law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth to be carefull enough of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Inheritance, ſhall bee content to ſeeke recompence where none is to be had, how doth the law offend in ſuppoſing this to be done for the beſt? and if it were done for the beſt, what injury ſhould the Heire ſuſtaine, or the law offer? beſides the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery being but a feoffment of Record in his owne nature changeth no uſe, except ſome new uſe be declared; neither ſhould I bee curious how theſe intailes were cut off (ſo as it were in forme of law) ſince me thinkes, it skills not whether an unthrifty twigge be cut off with a ſword, or with a hooke, for <hi>Major eſt diverſitas reſpectu mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie quam forme,</hi> and it is more reaſonable or naturall to accept a recompence of him that hath nothing, becauſe he may have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, then to provide for a poſſibility of eſcheat, whereto the aſpect of our law hath never reached, becauſe it is unnaturall.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59742:12"/>Thus you have partly heard what Divine and humane lawes eſteeme of Inheritances, and have entailes prepoſterouſly altering the forme of Inheritances are valued.</p>
               <p>And laſtly that the cutting off by Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is lawfull enough, ſo as it bee to a lawfull end, and that to reſtore the common law to her proper and moſt ancient courſe is an Act well deſerving; but this hath bin gathered on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the lawes: and the next that follow in order are the perſons, who of neceſſity muſt be either Donors, Donees or their heires: the Donors are either parents, or ſtrangers: by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, I meane principally the father who is called ſo of <hi>pantater, quaſi omnia ſervans,</hi> which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymology doth well expreſſe the office of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to conſiſt principally in providing and keeping for his Children, in reſpect of whom he is onely a father; and this naturall care and fatherly proviſion our common law ſeemeth to favour: for whereas feoffments made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſtrangers, if they be not cloathed with good and valuable conſideration, the uſe of the gift is not changed, but the donee remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſeiſed to the uſe of the donor for want
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59742:13"/>
of reciprocall exchange of gaine; yet if the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infeoffeth his child, the conſideration of fatherly affection is prized recompence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to change the uſe, and this holds true of all conſanguinity: but the heire which is ſo called <hi>ab haerendo, quia haereditas ſibi haeret,</hi> hath in law a more mutuall valuation with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a greater intereſt in the Inheritance then the younger ſort; for if the heire endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his wife by the conſent of his father, this endowment is good; and if the ſonne dyes, the wife ſhall have her dower though the father liveth, but this holdeth not of the younger ſonnes, by which it appeares that our law ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the heire an intereſt in his Inheritance during his fathers life; but if this ſhould ſeeme ſtrange, then may it bee more plainly proved out of Mr. <hi>Glauvile,</hi> who putting ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>quaeſtum, &amp; haereditas,</hi> ſaith that the Common law would not ſuffer the father to give any part of his Inheritance to his yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſonnes without the conſent of his heire, his words to that purpoſe are theſe, <hi>ſi quis plures habuerit filios mulieratos, non poterit de facili praeter conſenſum haeredis ſui filio ſuo poſt-nato de haereditate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59742:13"/>
ſuâ quantamlibet partem donare.</hi> If any man ſhal have divers ſonnes lawfully begotten, he may not eaſily without his heires conſent give any part of his Inheritance to his yonger ſonne and yet after he granteth that the father may give part to a ſtranger, or to his baſtard, which might ſeeme hard, if he had not ſhewed the reaſon thereof, viz. <hi>quia ſi hoc eſſet permiſſum, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cideret inde frequens prius natorum filiorum exhaere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatio propter maiorem patrum affectionem quam ſaepe erga poſt-natos ſuos habere ſolent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus may you ſee how much our law eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and defendeth the birth-right of the heire, not onely in giving him private power by the conſent of his father to endow his wife, but likewiſe in reſtraining the father from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his peculiar affection in beſtowing his Inheritance contrary to the meaning of the law, and this for ought I know remaineth law to this day; neither is it unreaſonable that the heire whom the law onely burdeneth with deſcents of warranties debts, and ſuch like, ſhould by the law reape onely the advantage of Inheritances.</p>
               <p>Much more equally therefore hath our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59742:14"/>
common law provided for our heires, then theſe abortive eſtates taile; and yet of entailes I confeſſe, that ſome are more tollerable then others, becauſe they doe leſſe manacle the pure and naturall courſe of Inheritances: for when lands are given to the eldeſt ſonne, and to the heires of his body, this varieth not much in the order of deſcent from fee-ſimple, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the immediate heire male or female ſhall by this gift enjoy the Inheritance otherwiſe due, and were it not for defrauding Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and abaſing the price when a ſale is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, and ſome other inconveniences, I ſhould thinke it juſt; but if lands be given to a man and to his wife, and the heires of their two bodies, if the wife dying leave but a daughter, though afterwards the Husband marrying againe hath iſſue a ſonne and dyes, by this gift entaile the daughter ſhall diſ-inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the ſonne againſt the expreſſe rule of all lawes. Againe if lands bee given to the heire apparent, and to the heires males of his body, with remainder over to the heires male, by this gift the heires generally are againſt all right robbed of the birth-right: which faſhion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59742:14"/>
of reſtraining of Inheritances from their due forme doth ſeeme to me moſt unjuſt; and this I affirme the rather becauſe wee find no ſuch gift expreſſed in the ſtatute of <hi>Weſt</hi> 2. though I confeſſe they are taken to be comprehended within the meaning thereof; but becauſe this word heires in his equivocate ſence hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers wayes to be underſtood, it were meete I ſhould diſcover my meaning thereby, which principally intendeth the firſt begotten ſon, who onely can bee heire according to maſter <hi>Glanvils primogenitus patri ſuccedit in totum, ita quod nullus ſuorum fratrum partem inde jure petere poteſt,</hi> the firſt begotten ſonne ſucceedeth the father in all, ſo as none of his brethren can lawfully claime any part thereof, in whoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the ſecond brother ſucceedeth, and ſo in order; and in want of brothers the ſiſters are heires: for Mr. <hi>Glanvile</hi> likewiſe ſaith, that <hi>ſi non reperiantur fratres, vocandae ſunt ſorores quibus praemortuis eorum liberi vocantur.</hi> And this hath not onely bin a continuall practiſe of the common law, but it is likewiſe well warranted by the Commandement of Almighty God, as may appeare by his Anſwer 23. <hi>Numbers,</hi> when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59742:15"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered unto him the petition of the daughters of <hi>Salphaad,</hi> when after their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death without ſonnes they demanded poſſeſſion of his Inheritance amongſt their Couſens, which was, <hi>Iuſtam rem poſtulant filiae Salphaad; da jis poſſesſioneminter cognatos patris ſui, et ei in haereditatem ſuccedant; ad filios autem Iſrael lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quêris haec: homo cum mortuus fuerit abſque filio, ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam tranſibit haereditas; ſi filiam non habuerit, habebit ſucceſsores fratres ſuos.</hi> The daughters of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaad</hi> doe aske that which is juſt, give them poſſeſſion among their fathers kindred, and let them ſucceed him in the Inheritance; and to the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> theſe things ſhalt thou ſpeake; when a man ſhall dye without a ſonne, the Inheritance ſhall paſſe to his daughter: if hee hath never a daughter, his brethren ſhall ſucceed: and this hath not bin onely comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but practiſed in all ages, for women have ſucceeded in Kingdomes, and in the greateſt Inheritances.</p>
               <p>If I have failed in the beginning of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to prove that Inheritances at our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law doe follow to all purpoſes their true patterne ſet forth in the lawes Divine,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59742:15"/>
let this I pray, ſerve for a full ſupply therein, ſince hereby you may perceive they agree to all intents, and leaſt we ſhould take this as a law limited to continue ſome ſhort time, it followeth, <hi>eritque hoc filiis Iſrael ſanctum lege per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum:</hi> worthily therefore was <hi>lex Voconia</hi> in the civill law, which excluded women from their Inheriting, abrogated as unworthy of the reputation of a law, ſince it ſwarveth from the forme of God his law; and to this purpoſe hath St. <hi>Auguſtine lib</hi> 3. <hi>De Civitate dei, lata eſt Romae lexilla Vocoium, ne quis haeredem foeim eam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret, necunicam filiam: qua lege quid iniquius dici aut cogitari posſit ignoro.</hi> The <hi>Voconian</hi> law is made at <hi>Rome,</hi> by which it is prohibited that daughters or a daughter ſhall inherit, then which law I know not what can bee ſaid or deviſed more wicked; who is he that underſtanding the high pleaſure of Almighty God concerning the beſtowing of his Inheritance, but would fearefully alter a law ſo everlaſtingly hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? and what ſonne perceiving that his father through ignorance had offended this law, and knowing that hee hath power to amend this fault, but he will without feare and with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59742:16"/>
all ſpeed endeavour to ſettle his Inheritance in ſuch courſe as hee undoubtedly knowes ſhall beſt pleaſe Almighty God?</p>
               <p>But leaſt I dwell too long on this point, I muſt ſpeake ſomewhat of the inſtrument or meanes whereby entailes are made, which ſometimes impaire, ſometimes amend that which is made.</p>
               <p>Entailes therefore are either accompliſhed by feoffment, by deed, or by teſtament.</p>
               <p>Feoffment is a gift or grant performed by delivery of ſeizin.</p>
               <p>A deed is an inſtrument likewiſe conſtuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, conveying ſome eſtate by inrolement.</p>
               <p>A teſtament is the juſt ſentence of the mind. All which do agree in one point. viz. that our wills and conſents are the cauſes without the which not any of them can be perfected; for as the teſtament is onely the will of the teſtator, ſo is neither a feoffment nor deed worth ought, but by the conſent and will of the feoffer or donor. And as they agree in this (which is all the ſubſtance of a teſtament) ſo doe they differ in the ſolemnity or maner of accompliſhing.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:59742:16"/>For our law preventing raſhnes in paſſing ſo large an eſtate as a Leaſe for life, or an eſtate of Inheritance, have to feoffments and deeds knit a neceſſity of Livery, and inrollment to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as pregnant witneſſes that the feoffment or deed was made by good advice, but to wills though they be of no force during the life of the Teſtator, no other ſolemnity is required but the death of him that made them, which prevents all posſibility to amend ought that is amiſſe.</p>
               <p>Another difference you may likewiſe note, (which I have, though to another purpoſe) touched before, viz. deeds and feoffments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire recompence to make the uſe change, but wills doe paſſe the eſtate they containe, and the uſe without regard of recompence; theſe imperfections and differences were the cauſe why wills were not entertained in our common law, or at moſt but in ſome cuſtomary places, as in <hi>Burgh Engliſh</hi> where becauſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances by thoſe cuſtomes deſcended to the youngeſt ſonne; the common law therefore in favour as I gheſſe of the heire, permitted there the uſe of wills as a meanes to reduce the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59742:17"/>
lands to th'heire at common law, and this I gheſſe ſo, becauſe in the common law they were utterly diſabled to convey Inheritances before the ſtatute of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. except as I have ſaid, where cuſtome had uſurped on the common law.</p>
               <p>And well was it conſidered in my judgment, that Acts done at ſo unfit times as wills are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made, ſhould not diſpoſe of matters of ſo great weight as Inheritances, for our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thought it not lawfull in extreames of ſicknes, by feoffments to paſſe their Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in <hi>extremis tamen agenti non eſt hoc cuiquam hactenus permiſſum, quia posſit tuncimmodica fieri here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatis diſtributio, ſi fuiſſet hoc permiſſum illiqui fervo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re paſsionis inſtantes et memoriam et rationem amittit.</hi> But to a man in extremity of ſicknes this is not permitted, becauſe then an immoderate diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of the Inheritance might bee made, if this were lawfull to him who looſeth his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and reaſon by the fervour of his preſent paſſion. This was the common law in Mr. <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile</hi> his time, and yet remaineth for ought I have read, whoſe authority I doe often remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as moſt worthy, being one of the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59742:17"/>
Iudges of our law, who as he hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this of feoffments, ſo of wills he ſaith, <hi>poſsit tamen huju ſmodi donatio in ultima voluntate alicui facta ita tenere, ſi cum conſenſu heredis, &amp; ex ſuo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu confirmaretur,</hi> yet ſaith hee, ſuch a gift made by will to any man may hold, ſo as it be made by the conſent of the heire, and confirmed by his conſent; moſt juſt therefore in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is our common law herein, which ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the father in extremity of ſicknes to diſpoſe of his Inheritance, ſince few men pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the meſſengers of death can afford reaſon his proper uſe.</p>
               <p>Since therefore wills are for the moſt part made rather out of fervor of paſſion then by adviſed deliberation of the mind, and ſince ſom are made by compulſion, other by ignorance, and ſome to content the importunity of others, when yet they hope to live longer then they happen, in all which caſes they are eſteemed as no wills, for <hi>voluntas eſt que neque per vim neque per ignorantiam fit,</hi> ſince I ſay all theſe inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are likely to happen, and may ſcarcely bee avoyded in wills; as few eſtates taile are much to be regarded, ſo none leſſe then ſuch as are compoſed by will: unworthy therefore ſhall I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59742:18"/>
eſteeme this inſtrument to have power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Inheritances, though it bee permitted by a late ſtatute.</p>
               <p>But ſince the Civill Law is the true mother and maintainer of wills, it were not amiſſe to ſhew you that therein the power of wills is not abſolute in diſpoſing of Inheritances, which any man that doubts may ſee in the Title of <hi>Querela inofficioſi,</hi> which is ſaid to be <hi>ſubſidiarium remedium à quo petitur a iudice ut teſtamentum contra pietatis officium ex ſuo officio reſcindat, et datur libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris et parentibus, fratribus vero et ſororibus ſi turpes perſonae ſcriptae ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you may ſee that even the Civill law hath compasſion on Inheritances, and giveth the Children power as it were to Cancell their fathers wills if they be againſt the office of piety, and what almoſt can be more impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? on the fathers part then to diſ-inherit his firſt begotten Sonne, his iſſue, for none other cauſe then for that Almighty God who onely maketh heires, made his ſonnes heire, a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or daughters, and rather to ſubſtitute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother who can bee no more his heire then <hi>puer ſuppoſititius,</hi> that is, a Changling can bee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59742:18"/>
Child to her that never bare him, for <hi>nemo eſt heres viventis:</hi> how therefore ſhould one that liveth make an heire, ſince there can bee no heire till the father be dead.</p>
               <p>This act therefore as it is unnaturall, ſo is it impious, for all ſinnes are moſt grievous that are moſt unnaturall; but becauſe it may here be alleadged that wills import a charge or Commandement of the diviſion neceſſary to be obſerved, it behooveth me to prevent that objection.</p>
               <p>Which anſwer firſt therefore me thinkes it were abſurd to ſay generally, that all wills containe a necesſity to bee performed, ſince ſome wills are imposſible, other unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and many doubtfull to all; which if wee ſhould tye a necesſity of fulfilling, we ſhould force things unposſible, things unlawfull, and things doubtfull, which were very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet: but if ſome bind us, and ſome leave us at liberty, then muſt the difference proceed either of the perſons, or of the things deviſed, or ſome other circumſtances: touching the perſons, I make no doubt but ſome will call in queſtion the duty of the Child, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59742:19"/>
the benefit of the gift, to the father who beſtowes the gift, as a forceable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt me, to which duty I could give great power and reſpect, if it were onely ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the younger ſonnes: for ſince they cannot claime any right in the Lands devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but by the will, it were ſomewhat reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable that the father having for them injured his Inheritance, ſhould reſtraine them from doing more wrong, by plucking the Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of the heire.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, if the father deviſeth his Lands to his heire, becauſe if this deviſe had not beene made, the Inheritance ſhould not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding have deſcended to the heire, as it were hard to clog his free right by impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per condition, ſo it were reaſonable for him to uſe any lawfull meanes to cut off his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt fetters; for the common law ſaith, that if the father deviſeth Lands to his ſonne and heire in Fee-ſimple, the heire may waive or forſake the deviſe, and hold himſelfe in by deſcent, as if no will had beene ever made: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it is, if the deviſe bee to a younger brother, or to a ſtranger, who are onely tyed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59742:19"/>
to the power of the will, if they will enjoy their eſtates created by the will: this hath beene ſaid to prove unto you, that the fathers will is not of force abſolute to binde the heire where the Law inveſteth a former right in him, by which I could inferre that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers commandement being but an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his will, cannot be of any better force then his will. As lawfull therefore would I thinke it for the ſonne and heire to cut off an intaile deviſed by his father, notwithſtanding his implyed commandement to the contrary, as it is for him to ſeeke remedy for a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous wound given to him by his father in his diſpleaſure, though hee ſhould charge him to the contrary. But if this be not enough con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>imperium,</hi> or <hi>mandatum Patris,</hi> wee have a rule that ſaith, <hi>verba imperativa ad privatum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorem prolata necesſitatem non inferunt, ſed conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> If therefore ſome private favour hath bred this Commandement, as it appeareth moſt evidently that it hath, then doth it not inferre neceſſity, but Counſell, which Counſell may either bee followed or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, according to the conveniency of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59742:20"/>
cauſe. But ſince this counſell as I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, tendeth to the croſſing both of Gods Lawes, and the worlds, I would thinke that the heire ſhould very weakely be compelled to obey it, eſpecially if wee remember that <hi>Mandatum eſt temporarium, hoc eſt, mandantis morte expirare,</hi> which ſeemeth reaſonable, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that a commandement being a thing meerely perſonall, as given in the perſon of a father, muſt of neceſſity take his ending with the perſon, for <hi>quod perſonae coheret, morte extinguitur.</hi> And this holds againſt the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perſons in the world, for <hi>mortuus eſt rebus humanis exemptus,</hi> and therefore not allowed to moderate amongſt the living. If this therefore holdeth amongſt Princes, much more doth it hold among private perſons, betweene whom it hath no generall force while they are living, for though the wife oweth obedience to her Husband, yet if he commands her to releaſe her Dower, ſhee is not bound to obey him. So likewiſe if the father commands his heire to give his Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance from his Children, neither was this commandement lawfull in the father to give,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59742:20"/>
nor in the ſonne to obey, becauſe it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall in them both.</p>
               <p>But to weigh this matter more ſtrictly, it ſhall not bee amiſſe to looke into the policies inducing us to make eſtates tailes, and policies perſwading the contrary, which policies are beſt judged by their intentions, the principall inſpection whereof addeth or detracteth from either of them.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Baintons</hi> caſe I have noted onely one reaſon urged in the behalfe of theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes eſpeciall: viz. 1. the Fame of the giver this is divided into two branches, Fame in continuing in his Name with advancement, and Fame in being founder of a houſe. And firſt concerning the manner, it is a thing wherein we have no property, for ſometimes Dogges and Horſes are called by our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sir-names, and ſo are other men, and perhaps ſuch as are our enemies. And touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the founding of a Houſe, though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it a thing worthy of memory, yet were this foundation much better heſtowed on ſome of our neereſt bloud, and on ſuch as the law perſwades us ſo to doe, and ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59742:21"/>
may wee aſſure our ſelves, that this houſe, or houſes thus founded are our owne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing built upon our owne ground, I meane ſuch Children as are proceeding from our owne Loynes, by benefiting of whom wee benefit our ſelves, they being part of our ſelves, and this courſe is moſt juſt and freeſt from offences; for if wee leave our Inheritances to diſcend according to the motion of the Law, or beſtow them on whom they belong in law, if any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall happen, it may onely bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the offence of the law, by whoſe Act it is done without any partiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect either of Names or other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate affections, and who can bee ſafer from offending then hee which contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himſelfe within the compaſſe and Buckler of the Law, ſince <hi>ſub clypeo legis nemo decipi dicitur?</hi> And by this policy ſtrangers, or remote Couſins, ſhall not more triumph of your greater affection then your naturall and living Children; your Children ſhall neither tempt their charity, nor repine to ſee their Couſens
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59742:21"/>
enriched with that which is their right, nor repent their long obſerved duties to their fathers.</p>
               <p>But otherwiſe well may they thinke that father unkind who preferreth to a name which properly is none of his, before his owne bloud which aſſuredly is his; for it is plaine, that another man his name cannot bee mine, though pronounced and written to all purpoſes like mine, ſince every name (bee they alike or unlike) is peculiar to diſtinguiſh every perſon, and cannot bee common to another man and to mee, as <hi>Homo</hi> is to all men. But this my meaning is more evidently declared in the Lawes of Armory; for though my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Brother his Sonne beareth a name like mine to all purpoſes, yet as <hi>nullum ſimile eſt idem,</hi> ſo in his Coat Armour which belongs to his name, hee beareth a Creſſant for his fathers difference, which difference ſheweth the name and coat to be none of mine, ſince to my Armes due to my name no difference belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; whereas contrariwiſe my Daughters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59742:22"/>
by quartering my Coat Armour with their Husbands, doe moſt truely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent both my name and Armes, for as the Coat is knowne by the name, ſo mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the name is knowne by the Coat.</p>
               <p>Since therefore wee live in our heires after our deaths, it were good policy that as wee reſpect our eſtates while we live, ſo wee ſhould provide in like manner for thoſe in whom wee live after our deaths, viz. our lawfull heires. And hee that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth his Inheritance otherwiſe, in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion doth like him that hath a Hat made for his head, and weares it on his heele; or like him that gives all to his Couſins or friends till he beg himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Since therefore the Lawes of nature (which cannot bee diſpenſed withall) are contrary to eſtates in ſpeciall taile, in that moſt entailes convey unnaturally our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances from our heires to others, ſince the Divine written Lawes have expreſſed a forme of inheriting contrary to the forme of all entailes, which wee ought not to alter, becauſe <hi>praeceptum poſuit, et non praeteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59742:22"/>
Pſalme</hi> 144. and ſince the Common Lawes of this Realme doe expoſtulate their ancient formes of Inheritances, as moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious for publike good, and ſince the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this preſent time have committed power into your hands, whereby you may either benefit or prejudice your heires, for <hi>qui non defendit injuriam neque propulſat a ſuis cum poteſt, injuſte facit,</hi> and ſince <hi>nemini vim et injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am facere videtur qui ſuo jure utitur.</hi> Since the ſtatute of <hi>Weſt</hi> 2. neither commandeth, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth, nor puniſheth, but is onely a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive authority to doe that which before the Statute was unlawfull. And to conclude with Lawes, ſince as Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith, <hi>nitun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur leges humana cognintione atque humana prudentia, per quam non poteſt ſatis certò conſtituere de futuris,</hi> and ſince ſucceeding inconveniences by their common events have compelled our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to make breach into their conditionall gifts, in acknowledging the errors of them that firſt craved this liberty, I cannot ſee why you ſhould any longer continue that which deſerveth to be altered, except you thinke inventions of men better then the Lawes of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59742:23"/>
God. And hereſies in Law (which are ſaid to be ſometimes <hi>de immunitate</hi>) better then the ancient poſitive Lawes of this Realme, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you think that nature have more bound you to advance others then your owne Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, except you thinke that other men have begotten better Children then your ſelfe, except you more reſpect a like name of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the true diſcent of your owne bloud, except you mind to ſow hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your conſanguinity, except you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to offer open wrong to your heire, for <hi>paria ſunt malefacere, et malefacta non obviare,</hi> and except you would vainely and <hi>Babylonically</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a Tower againſt the omnipotent power of God himſelfe, which building cannot long ſtand, nor proſper. Be not therefore I beſeech you, miſled with the bad example of many that have bin negligent in cutting off en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes, for <hi>non minùs ardebunt qui cum multis arde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt,</hi> and <hi>multitudo delinquentium non excuſat pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> and though therefore many do offend in this manner as offenders for company, let them remember the fearefull curſe pronounced by the Prophet <hi>Eſa</hi> 24. <hi>terra infecta eſt ab habitato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59742:23"/>
ſuis qui tranſgreſſi ſunt leges, mutaverunt jus, et diſſipaverunt foedus ſempiternum: propter hoc male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio vorabit terram.</hi> And this I doe the rather apply to my preſent purpoſe, becauſe I could never (after long obſervation) find any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily continue in the heires male three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcents after an entaile made and continued to the heires male, by which I gheſſe they are not watered with heavenly blesſings. And with this I will conclude, ſaying that I will adde one doubt, viz. that though you will forbeare to cut off the entaile, yet are you not ſure, that they to whom you will leave it will doe ſo, and if they cut it off, you ſhall joyne hands with them in an unnaturall act.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
